# Arpon Kapuria

🔗 arpon-kapuria | 🗷 arpkapuria@gmail.com | 😯 GitHub | ♦ LeetCode | 🔰 +880 1797 288296

# Summary

A recent graduate in Computer Science with a deep passion for technology, research, and teaching. My goal is to inspire the next generation of learners and augment human intelligence with more capable artificial intelligence to improve our day-to-day life. Outside of this, I like traveling.

### Research Interests

Deep Learning, Representation Learning, Reasoning in AI Models (Language + Image)

## Education

# National Institute of Technology, Tiruchirappalli

B.Tech in Computer Science & Engineering | CGPA 7.75/10 (First Class)

Kushtia Government College, Kushtia

HSC (Science) | GPA 5/5

Kushtia Zilla School, Kushtia

SSC (Science) | GPA 5/5

December 2020 - June 2024

Tamil Nadu, India

2019

Kushtia, Bangladesh

2017

Kushtia, Bangladesh

# Relevant Courseworks

- Operating Systems
- Database Management Systems
- Data Structures and Algorithms
- Computer Networks

- Linear Algebra and Calculus
- Augmented and Virtual Reality
- Technical Writing
- Artificial Intelligence

- Machine Learning
- Deep Learning Techniques
- Natural Language Processing
- Image Processing and Applications

# Experience

# Indian Institute of Technology Bombay

Research Intern | MeDAL Lab

May 2023 - July 2023

Mumbai, India

#### Project 1: Enhancing Self Supervised Learning framework - BYOL

- Conducted an extensive literature survey on self-supervised learning, emphasizing contrastive learning principles and frameworks like simCLR, MoCo, and BYOL.
- Reproduced the BYOL framework using PyTorch, replicating the original work to establish a solid foundation for subsequent modifications.
- Introduced innovative changes to BYOL, such as formulating a new algorithm, incorporating a novel loss function, and architecture adjustments for a better representation learning. Hyperparameter tuning was conducted to optimize the training procedure.

#### Project 2: Radiology DICOM Image Anonymization

- Created a user-friendly system for DICOM image upload and processing using Flask, along with a Python script using Pydicom for efficient anonymization, addressing medical data privacy concerns.
- Performed a testing using the CRAFT model for text detection and extraction from X-ray images, enhancing the interpretability and utility of medical imaging data.

#### National Institute of Technology Tiruchirappalli

October 2022 - February 2023

UG Research Assistant | Industrial Automation Lab

Tiruchirappalli, India

#### Project: Centralized Power Cluster Home Automation

- Developed a Flutter app to automate the operations and billing for a power cluster in Assam, India, serving 200 homes.
- Integrated Flutter front-end with API developed in Django and used an MQTT server for IoT communication.
- This project was supported by the Dept. of Science & Technology, and Ministry of Science and Technology, Govt. of India, under the initiative SUSTENANCE (Sustainable Energy System for Achieving Novel Carbon Neutral Energy Communities).

# **Projects**

#### NoSmokeZone – AI for Smoker Detection in Public Spaces

December 2023 – January 2024

Python, TensorFlow, Keras, OpenCV

- Automated a real-time smoker detection system with minimal human intervention leveraging advanced CNN models (EfficientNetV2, VGG16, ResNet-50) and Vision Transformer, achieving 93% accuracy.
- Fine-tuned models and applied data augmentation techniques, enhancing robustness and reducing false positives/negatives by 7% compared to baseline models, significantly minimizing misclassifications.

#### 9 Box Puzzle - Android App

December 2022

Java, A\* Algorithm

- Designed and programmed an engaging 9-puzzle game in Java, featuring a 3x3 grid of numbered boxes from 1 to 8, with a missing 9th box in random order.
- Provided comprehensive in-app resources, including a home menu, how-to-play guide, optimal solution visualization, and a performance tracking system for user statistics and puzzle difficulty based on the minimum moves required.
- The optimal solution window displays step-by-step moves needed to solve the puzzle most efficiently, utilizing an AI-based algorithm (A\* Algorithm).

# Malicious Website Detection Using Machine Learning

September 2022 - November 2022

Python, Flask, HTML/CSS, JavaScript

- Implemented a machine-learning model with around 94% accuracy to detect malicious websites.
- Trained and compared different models using K-Nearest Neighbor, Support Vector Machine, Logistic Regression, and Multi Layer Perceptron to obtain a better performance.
- Built a chrome extension using JavaScript to extract the features from the webpage to test the website against the trained model to classify if it is malicious or not. Added a feature to receive user feedback.
- Adopted a continual learning approach to store the user feedback and retrain the model daily to improve performance.

#### Skills

Programming Languages: C, C++, Python, Dart, JavaScript, SQL

Frameworks: PyTorch, LangChain, FastAPI, Flutter, Unity

Database: MySQL, MongoDB, Chroma (Vector DB)

Miscellaneous: Linux, Docker, Prometheus, Git, VS Code, Android Studio, Google Colab, Latex

Languages: Bengali (Native), English (Advanced), Hindi (Verbal), German (A1.1)

Standarized Test Scores: GRE - 307, IELTS - 7.5 (2024)

### Achievements

Recipient of the prestigious ICCR Scholarship by the Ministry of External Affairs, Govt. of India, for fully funded undergraduate studies, awarded for academic excellence and promoting cultural exchange.

2017 SSC Board Merit Order Scholarship from the Chamber of Commerce, Kushtia, Bangladesh.

2015 JSC General Grade Scholarship from the Government of Bangladesh.

2012 1st position, Zilla Shilpakala Academy Kushtia organized Art competition for Independence Day.

2011 2nd position, Bangladesh Udichi Shilpigoshthi Kushtia organized Art competition for Bengali New Year ' 1418.

#### References

 Dr. M. Brindha Associate Professor,

Department of Computer Science & Engineering

NIT Trichy, India - 620015

brindham@nitt.edu

2. Amit Sethi, PhD

Professor, Department of Electrical Engineering

IIT Bombay, India - 400076

asethi@iitb.ac.in